A Guide to the Population Council records, Ford Foundation Projects, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 6 FA1293
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council records, Ford Foundation Projects, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 6
1959-1975
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council.
FA1293
9.93 Cubic Feet 21 LGL size Hollinger Boxes
Scope and Contents
This series documents the family planning program activities and administrative operations of the Tunisia and Ceylon Population Council Regional Offices. The Offices were supported through grants provided by the Ford Foundation. They generally focused on collecting statistics related to acceptance and use of contraceptives and family planning services by local populations, projecting population trends, supporting national family planning programs like l'Office National du Planning Familial et de la Population(National Office of Family Planning and Population) in Tunisia and the Family Planning Bureau in Ceylon (present day Sri Lanka), conducting family planning related research, providing and participating in family planning education programs and services, and collaborating on family planning projects with international agencies like the United States Agency for International Development (USAID), the Swedish International Development Authority (SIDA), the World Bank, and various United Nations organizations.
Files are organized by the Office to which they pertain. Records within the Tunisia Office files are more project and program focused whereas records within the Ceylon Office files are more administration focused. In addition to containing a group of office files created by the Tunisia regional Population Council post, the series also includes a group of press clippings that the Tunisia Office staff members had collected during the course of their duties.
Arrangement
This series is arranged into 3 subseries. The suberies arrangement is as follows:
1. Tunisia Office files, 1959-1975
2. Tunisia Office collected press clippings, 1964-1973, bulk 1969-1971
3. Ceylon Office files, 1960-1971, bulk 1967-1971
Biographical / Historical
The Population Council was founded by John D. Rockefeller 3rd in 1952 to undertake "significant activities in the broad field of population." Its goal has been to bring about a reduction in the number of births that occur in the world. In Its early years, the business of the Population Council was conducted by a Demographic Division and a Biomedical Division. Through its Demographic Division, the Council sought to document what it conceived to be an overpopulation problem threatening many areas of the world. To accomplish this purpose, the Division facilitated research on the economic, social, and psychological factors which affect the growth and decline of human population. This Council-assisted research effort was conducted not only by staff of the Demographic Division but also by other institutions and scholars, some of whom received Council grants and fellowships and some of whom received informal advice and consultation on how to design and execute studies.
The Biomedical Division, which, beginning in 1959, occupied a laboratory at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), has conducted pure and applied research on plant, animal, and human reproductive physiology and on the development, the physiological action, and the safety and effectiveness of contraceptive methods. The Council facilitated similar types of medical research by non-Council scientists at other institutions by giving grants and fellowships for such research. The Council's biomedical research and its support for research by non-Council scientists were instrumental in the development of the modern intrauterine coil and the birth control pill.
In about 1960, the scope of Population Council activities expanded. The Council began to render practical and technical aid to foreign nations. Beginning in that year, the Demographic Division, in addition to supervising research, became involved in Pakistan's family planning program, extending practical and technical aid in organizing and running a national family planning program. By 1964 the Council's Demographic Division had assisted in organizing family planning programs in South Korea, Taiwan, Thailand, Tunisia, and Turkey. In that year, the Council created the Technical Assistance Division. This division, in ensuing years, continued the assistance of the Council in the countries where it had already become involved and also helped start and run programs in India, Morocco, the Philippines, and Puerto Rico.
An underlying aim of the Council's grant programs has been to encourage the development and growth of institutions that would promote family planning programs. To this end, the Council has given grants and advice to various universities and research centers for starting and upgrading programs for demographic and biomedical training and research programs; has assisted the United Nations to set up and expand regional Demographic Training and Research Centres in Bombay, India, Santiago, Chile, and Cairo, Egypt; has worked with the Ford Foundation on family planning programs in Pakistan, India, and North Africa.
In addition to rendering technical aid and sponsoring research, the Council has undertaken several complementary public relations efforts. To reach the general populations of the United States and of foreign nations, Council officers have worked to inform the mass media about population issues and to encourage magazine articles, movies, and books dealing with population matters. Council officers and representatives have also made trips and prepared reports to convince various foreign government leaders of the importance and the desirability of promulgating family planning programs. In addition, Council officers participated in and helped organize and finance conferences for demographers and medical scientists active in population work.
The Population Council has obtained its financial support through large contributions. The Ford and Rockefeller Foundations and the Rockefeller Brothers Fund have been the principal institutional supporters of the Council. John D. Rockefeller 3rd has been the single most significant individual backer of the Council.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Population Council records include:
FA210 Population Council records, Accession 1
FA432 Population Council records, Record Group 2, Accession 2
FA1294 Population Council records, Morocco Office Files, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 7
FA775 Population Council records, Index
FA092 Population Council photographs
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of the RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Population Council records were initially deposited at the RAC in 1976. The terms of deposit were subsequently amended in the year 2000.
Abortion; Birth control; Contraceptives; Family planning services; Fertility, Human; International cooperation; Maternal health services; Overpopulation; Population; Population forecasting; Population policy; Population research; Sterilization (Birth control); Ford Foundaton; World Bank; World Health Organization; United States. Agency for International Development; International Planned Parenthood Federation
- Tunisia Office files, 1959-1975; 1; 3.5 Cubic Feet 8 LGL sized Hollinger Boxes
  Arrangement
  Original order has largely been retained in relation to the sequence of the files. Therefore, records concerning the same organization or subject may appear in several different sections of the series under similar or identical titles. Moreover, because the file names were written in both English and French, similar records may appear under titles in different languages.
  To conduct a thorough search for records on a given topic, it is essential to look for material in as many different sections of the series and under as many different names or titles as possible.
  Scope and Contents
  This subseries contains correspondence, memoranda, reports, tables, surveys, and clinic forms related to the family planning program activities of the Tunisia Population Council Office. Chief correspondents include Population Council Resident Advisors Dr. Melvyn C, Thorne (1968-1972), Joseph A. Grinblat (1972-1973, formerly Research and Evaluation Advisor from 1969-1972), and Alain J. Marcoux. The subseries houses much of the Resident Advisors' (also referred to as Counseiller Residents and Representatives) correspondence with: 1) Population Council officials like Joel Montague, Regional Director, and Robert J. Lapham, Program Research and Evaluation; 2) Partnering international agencies like the United States Agency for International Development (USAID), the World Bank, the World Health Organization (WHO), and the International Planned Parenthood Federation (IPPF); and 3) Different Heads of the various national family planning programs in Tunisia. The different program Heads include Dr. Amor Daly, Dr. Abderrahman Mzelini, Dr. Ben Samil, Dr. T. B. Ben Cheikh, Dr. Mohsen Bahri, Chedli Tnani, and Mezri Chekir. Within the subseries, reports and correspondence document the organizational evolution of the various national family planning programs in Tunisia up until l'Office National du Planning Familial et de la Population (National Office of Family Planning and Population) was official established in 1973. Previous incarnations of the program include Direction Exterieure du Planning Familial, Direction du Planning Familial et de la Protection Maternelle et Infantile, and l'Institut National du Planning Familial et de la Protection Maternelle et Infantile.
  Many materials document the Office's data collection activities in relation to demographic surveys, population projections, and family planning program service statistics. Also prevalent within the subseries are records concerning the Office's engagement with family planning conferences and educational programs. Correspondence, reports, promotional materials, invitations, and lists of attendees provide evidence of the Office's participation in these activities.
  The End-of-Tour reports by Thorne and Grinblat may prove particularly helpful to researchers seeking to learn more about the organizational history and program performance of the Population Council office in Tunisia. Furthermore, many files within the subseries include description notes that summarize their contents. These notes were likely compiled by previous processing archivists and may not fully or accurately describe the materials of every file.
  Materials in the subseries refer to Grinblat as both Joseph and Jofred Grinblat.
  - Organisation du Planning Familial et de la Protection Maternelle et Infantile, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes file description note.
  - North Africa Review Team, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Contains description note for contents of this file as well the North Africa Review Team, 1972 file located in Box: 1, Folder 3.
  - North Africa Review Team, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Description note for the contents of this file is included within the North Africa Review Team, 1971-1973 file located in Box: 1, Folder: 2.
  - Maternal and Child Health Centers, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes description note for the contents of this file as well as the contents of the Maternal and Child Health Centers, 1961-1971 file, located in Box: 1, Folder: 5.
  - Maternal and Child Health Centers, 1961-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Description note for this file is included within the Maternal and Child Health Centers, 1970-1973 file, located in Box: 1, Folder 4.
  - Family Planning Program service statistics, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Narrative report to the Ford Foundation, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Teaching by Population Council members, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Questions posees aux hygienistes, Dr. Melvyn C. Thorne, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - International conferences in Tunisia, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes description note for the contents of this file as well as the contents of the International Conferences in Tunisia, 1968 files located in Box: 2, Folder: 11 and Box: 2, Folder 12.
  - International conferences in Tunisia, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Description note for this file is included within the International conferences in Tunisia, 1968-1970 file, located in Box: 2, Folder: 10.
  - International conferences in Tunisia, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - International conferences in Tunisia, miscellaneous, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence on statistics, 1967-1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Demography, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - E.N.D weighting coefficients, correspondence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - KAP (Knowledge, Attitude, Practice) surveys, 1968-1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    File description note included.
  - Medical Division of the Office National du Planning Familial et de la Population, circa 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Medical: Miscellaneous, 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Seminars on family planning in Tunisia, 1963-1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Demography, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Includes description note for the contents of this file as well as the contents of the Demography, 1968-1969 file, located in Box: 3, Folder: 22.
  - Demography, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    The description note for this file is included within the Demography, 1970-1971 file, located in Box: 3, Folder: 21.
  - Reports and evaluation, 1966-1972 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Includes description note for the contents of this file as well as the contents of the Reports and evaluation, 1965-1968 file, located in Box: 3, Folder: 24.
  - Reports and evaluation, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Description note for this file is included within the Reports and evaluation, 1966-1972 file, located in Box: 3, Folder: 23.
  - History: Documents of family planning, Tunisia, George F. Brown, 1959-1969 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Microeconomics Roundtable, 1968-1972 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Includes description note for the contents of this file as well as the contents of the Microeconomics Roundtable, 1969-1972 file, located in Box: 3, Folder: 27.
  - Microeconomics Roundtable, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Description note for this file is located within the Microeconomics Roundtable, 1968-1972 file located in Box: 3 Folder: 26.
  - Research projects: Special Advance Account, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Ligature des trompes, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Family Planning: Organization of Official Program of the Tunisian Government, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Reports regarding family planning, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Projet de primes et indemnites, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Avortements, 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Separated Materials
    An oversized item titled Tabulations of abortions has been removed from the file in order to be moved to a flat storage container. This item has been assigned the unique separation number 2017:FA1293:001.
  - Depo-Provera study, 1969-1975 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Liste des secretaires regionnaux de Family Planning, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - KAP (Knowledge Attitude Practice) surveys, 1964-1973 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Project World Bank, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Courses and fellowships, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    Includes description note for the contents of this file as well as the contents of the Courses and fellowships, 1968-1969 file, located in Box: 4, Folder: 39.
  - Courses and fellowships, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    Description note for this file is included within the Courses and fellowships, 1966-1970 file, located within Box: 4, Folder: 38.
  - Coordination of donors in Tunisia, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - United States Congress and American universities, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    File also contains a letter from Population Council Resident Advisor Dr. Melvyn C. Thorne to Texas Congressman George H. W. Bush in which Thorne advocates United States sponsorship of in-country training programs for specialists in the field of family planning services. The programs Thorne described would prepare specialists to address specific, local problems within their own countries instead of sending them away for training they would then have to adapt to fit the circumstances of their home environments.
    Bush served as the Chairman of the Republican Taskforce on Earth Resources and Population. Other pieces of correspondence in the file document the Taskforce's interest in the Population Council's activities in developing countries.
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development and miscellaneous, 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - United States Agency for International Development, Melvyn C. Thorne file, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - World Bank, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Administrative and operating structure: Tunisian Family Planning, 1969-1973 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Reports: Joseph A. Grinblat and Alain J. Marcoux, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    File contains Grinblat's End-of-Tour Report and Marcoux' Report on Research and Evaluation in Tunisia.
  - Matronnes or granny midwives, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Situation appraisal of Tunisian Family Planning Program, 1967-1974 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Islam and family planning: Muslim attitudes, 1968-1975 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Paramedical training, 1968-1973 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Special projects: Miscellaneous, 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Developments, 1967-1972 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Memos to Heads of Family Planning, 1968-1974 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Program administration and organization, 1968-1973 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - SERETES, Bizerte Project, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - United States Agency for International Development, 1964-1972 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - World Bank, 1969-1973 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Family planning instruction in French, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Mobile teams, 1970-1975 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Memoranda: Family Planning, general, 1969-1974 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Letters and memoranda to officials and persons other than Family Planning, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Family Well-Being campaigns, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Laws: Papers, studies, reports, and correspondence, 1963-1975 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Population Council "Monthly" Reports, October 1966-December 1969 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    Includes description note for the contents of this file as well as the contents of the files: Population Council "Monthly" Reports, January 1970-August 1971; Population Council "Monthly" Reports, July 1973-October 1975; Reports: Trips, End-of-Tour, and others, 1967-1975; Miscellaneous monthly reports, September 1967-July 1970; Population Council reports: Other than monthly, 1974-1975; Report: End-of-Tour, Joseph A. Grinblat, 1973; Correspondence on reports, 1974-1975, all located within Box 6: Folders: 65-72.
  - Population Council "Monthly" Reports, January 1970-August 1971 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    Description note for this file is included within the Population Council "Monthly" Reports, October 1966-December 1969 file, located in Box: 6, Folder: 65.
  - Population Council "Monthly" Reports, July 1973-October 1975 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Reports: Trips, End-of-Tour, and others, 1967-1975 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Miscellaneous monthly reports, September 1967-July 1970 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Population Council reports: Other than monthly, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Report: End-of-Tour, Joseph A. Grinblat, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Correspondence on reports, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - New forms, 1970-1974 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Contraceptive supplies, not directly Family Planning Program, 1966-1975 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Memos regarding statistics and statistical reports, circa 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Releves des activites des Centres de Planning Familial: Program statistics, June 1964-December 1966 (Box 7, Folder 76)
    Includes description note for the contents of this file as well as the contents of the files: Releves des activites des Centres de Planning Familial: Program statistics, 1966-1967; Releves des activites des Centres de Planning Familial: Program statistics, 1968; Releves des activites des Centres de Planning Familial: Program statistics, January 1969-June 1969, all located within Box: 7, Folders: 77-79.
  - Releves des activites des Centres de Planning Familial: Program statistics, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 77)
    Description note for this file is included within the Releves des activites des Centres de Planning Familial: Program statistics, June 1964-Deember 1966 file, located in Box: 7, Folder: 76.
  - Releves des activites des Centres de Planning Familial: Program statistics, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Releves des activites des Centres de Planning Familial: Program statistics, January 1969-June 1969 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - United Nations program for aid to Tunisia, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 80)
    File contains a single bound publication by the Programme des Nations Unies Pour le Development, Tunis.
  - Memorandum to Dr. Amor Daly, 1967-1969 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - World Health Organization Conference on Human Reproduction, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - World Health Organization 2nd Journee D'Avril, 1969-1972 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Liste des Centres de Planning Familial au 31-12-1970, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Rapport de Fin de Mission, Jacques Vallin, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - L'enquete Nabeul, 1973-1975 (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Projet d'Integration de la Planification Familiale dans les Activites Sanitaires Existantes du Cap Bon, circa 1972 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Statistics: Live births, program facilities and personnel, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Reports, 1964-1968 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Studies: "Controle des Entrees", Generalisation du Nouveau Systeme d'Enregistrement Statistique, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Jendouba Educational Project, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Research designs, general, 1971-1973 (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Centre d'Etudes et de Recherches Economiques et Sociales Grant D70 .81, 1970-1974 (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - Reports and memos to the Files, Dr. Melvyn C. Thorne, 1964-1972 (Box 8, Folder 95)
  - Outpatient Department clinic form, Montfleury Clinic, 1971-1974 (Box 8, Folder 96)
    Inludes file description note.
  - Population Council monthly reports and other Family Planning related material, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 97)
  - History of Family Planning in Tunisia, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 98)
  - Research and evaluation, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 99)
  - Doctors in Tunisia, circa 1967-1974 (Box 8, Folder 100)
  - Abortion, 1968-1972 (Box 8, Folder 101)
  - Memos to the Files, Elizabeth E. Mueller, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - Bourguiba - Speeches on Family Planning, 1970 (Box 19, Folder 219)
  - Demographic Surveys - Cap Bon, 1973-1975 (Box 19, Folder 220)
  - Enquele National sur les Attitudes de Population Face au Planning Familial (Box 19, Folder 221)
  - Enquete C. A. P., 1970-1971 (Box 19, Folder 222)
  - Budget - Population Council - Tunisia, 1972-1975 (Box 19, Folder 223)
  - Miscellaneous Studies, Annual Reports on Family Planning Program, 1970-1971 (Box 19, Folder 224)
  - Depoprovera - Aziza Othmana, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 225)
  - Country Profile, 1972 (Box 19, Folder 226)
  - Programs for Population Education, 1967-1971 (Box 19, Folder 227)
- Tunisia Office collected press clippings, 1964-1975; 2; 2 Cubic Feet About 4.25 LGL size Hollinger Boxes